[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-four]
[第二十四集]
This morning's congressional inquiry session
今天上午的国会质询会
The main topics to be discussed are
主要讨论的议题是
Submitted by Mr. Yi Yilong Zhang Changli
易夔龙 张长礼议员提交的
Severely punish Cai Yuanpei, president of Peking University
[蔡元培 字 孑民 北京大学校长]
Indulge Chen Duxiu Hu Shi and others.
纵容陈独秀 胡适等人
Advocate a new culture
鼓吹新文化
Covering Confucius and Mencius' ethics
覆孔孟 铲伦常的
Disturb moral thought
扰乱道德思想
Proposals that endanger social order
危害社会秩序的提案
There are three agendas.
议程有三
The sponsor explains the proposal.
一 提案人做提案说明
Inquiry debate
二 质询辩论
1. Members vote
三 议员表决
First of all, please ask the first signatory of the proposal
首先 请提案第一署名人
Yi Long made a proposal explanation.
易夔龙做提案说明
Where's Yi Kuilong?
易夔龙呢
not be in
不在
He is not coming, is he?
他这是不来了吧
Mr. Zhang Changli
张长礼议员
Mr yi yilong did not attend the meeting.
易夔龙议员没有到会
What is the reason for this?
这是什么原因啊
Really didn't come
真没来啊
Mr. Yi Long
易夔龙议员
There must be something special going on.
肯定是遇到了什么特殊的情况
Can't be present
不能到场
In a situation like this
像这种情况
Congress used to meet it all the time.
以前国会也是经常碰到的
I think that although the sponsor was not present
我认为 虽然提案人没有到场
But the proposal has not been withdrawn.
但是提案并没有撤销
That is to say, the proposal can still be valid
也就是说 提案依然可以有效
We don't affect the voting on the proposal.
我们并不影响对提案的表决呀
Right vote
对  表决
Let's vote.
表决吧
Voting voting
表决 表决 表决
We have to wait for the senator
得等议员来
With what vote?
凭什么表决
Nobody's here yet.
人都没来呢
everyone
各位
Councilman Yi Long may not be able to come because of something urgent.
议员易龙可能有急事来不了
The second sponsor, Mr. Zhang Changli
第二提案人张长礼议员
Propose to ignore the proposal description.
提议忽略提案说明
And inquiry theory.
和质询辩论两个环节
Go directly to the vote.
直接进入表决
What objections do Members have?
各位议员有何异议呀
Mr. Speaker, I protest
议长先生 我表示抗议
An open Senate of the country
堂堂国家的参议院
Issue a formal notice of
发出的正式通知
Let me answer the question.
让我来接受质询
Now it's casual.
现在居然随随便便
Inexplicably cancel the inquiry translation theory
莫名其妙地取消质询译论
This is to take the dignity of the country
这是拿国家的尊严
Play games with the personality of citizens.
和公民的人格做儿戏
I can not accept
我不能接受
Don't promise either.
也不答应
You're right. We protest
说得对 我们抗议
I think Mr Cai Zimin's protest
我认为蔡孑民先生的抗议
It makes sense.
是有道理的
You want to impeach him?
你们要弹劾他
And don't let him participate in the theory.
又不让他参加论
What is the meaning of this?
这是什么意思
It's called punishment without teaching.
这就叫不教而诛
I won't agree.
我是不会同意的
Mr Yi Long, the first sponsor, was not present.
第一提案人易夔龙议员不在场
But the second sponsor, Mr. Zhang Changli, was present.
但第二提案人张长礼议员在场
It should be done by him
应该由他来进行
The proposal and the theory are.
提案说明和辩论才是
exactly
没错
Zhang Changli explained
张长礼 说明 说明
Explanation
说明 说明
Explain.
说明 说明一下
everyone
各位
Ladies and gentlemen, this proposal
各位 这个提案
It's mainly done by Mr. Yi Yilong.
主要是易夔龙议员做的
I just seconded it.
我只是附议而已
I can't make this explanation.
我做不了这个说明
I think the proposal itself
我认为这个提案本身
The problem has been made very clear.
已经把问题说得很清楚了
Especially a lot of content.
尤其是许多的内容
It has been published in major newspapers.
已经在各大报纸公开发表了
Its reliability is beyond doubt.
它的可靠性是不可置疑的
I think
我认为
Vote without argument.
不要辩论即可表决
Voting voting
表决 表决 表决
No vote
不表决
Must debate
必须辩论
Voting debate
表决 辩论
Voting voting
表决 表决 表决
Mr. Speaker
议长先生
I'd like to ask this Member Zhang.
我想请问一下这位张议员
What evidence do you have to prove it?
您有哪些证据可以证明
The newspaper attacked President Cai Yuanpei.
报纸上攻击蔡元培校长
And professor Chen Duxiu's content is true.
还有陈独秀教授的内容是真实的
So many newspapers rushed to report.
那么多的报纸争相报道
lengthy and tedious
连篇累牌
Is everyone faking it?
难道大家都在作假吗
I am not a student of Peking University.
[赵世炎 字 琴生 北京高等师范附中学生]
But I was a reporter.
但我当过记者
I've done a fragrance check on this matter.
这件事情我做过调香查
Attack the vast majority of Peking University's manuscripts.
攻击北京大学的绝大多数稿件
It's all from a reporter named trample on people.
都出自于一个叫作踩人的记者
This reporter named trampling on people
这个叫踩人的记者
His real name is Zhang Fengzai.
真名叫作张丰载
This man is the nephew of Councillor Zhang Changli.
此人正是议员张长礼的侄子
Please ask Congressman Zhang Changli to explain.
请国会议员张长礼说明
Please explain to Congress.
请国会说明
And Zhang Fengzai.
还有张丰载
Zhang Changli explained
张长礼说明
protest
抗议
This is a shameless rumor and framing.
这是无耻的造谣和诬陷
I want to sue him.
我要控告他
You still have reason.
你还有理了
What's your relationship?
你们俩什么关系
Zhang Fengzai explained
张丰载说明
I can prove it.
我可以证明
Zhang Changli's nephew Zhang Fengzai
张长礼的侄子张丰载
By means of repeated deception
多次以欺骗的手段
Get our work-study mutual aid society.
获取我们工读互助社
Family background and personal data of members
社员的家庭背景和个人资料
He also wrote a famous article to spread rumors and cause trouble.
他还写匿名文章造谣生事
Frame Mr. Cai Yuanpei Chen Duxiu
栽赃蔡元培陈独秀先生
It's planted. It's
这是栽赃 这是诽谤
Do you have proof? Do you have proof?
你们有证据吗 有证据吗
Ask them if they have any evidence.
您问他们有证据吗
solemnly still
肃静 肃静
Be quiet
静一静
Sit down.
坐下 坐下
You are here at the National Conference Hall.
诸位 这里是国会议场
It is a sacred place.
是一个神圣的地方
Everything you say.
各位说出的每句话
There must be conclusive evidence.
都要有确凿的证据
I can prove it.
我可以证明
The speeches of the two students are true.
这两位同学的发言是真实的
This Zhang Fengzai
这个张丰载
It is Shenzhou Daily.
就是《神州日报》
Founder of Half Valley Newsletter
《半谷通讯》 创办人
Not only did he step on people himself.
他不仅自己以踩人的名义
Write articles to discredit Peking University.
写文章造谣抹黑北京大学
And pay for other journalists.
还花钱雇用其他记者
Help him publish and spread rumors.
帮他发稿散布谣言
this
这个
It was he who had it delivered to me yesterday.
就是他昨天让人给我送来的
And commission.
稿件和佣金
Besides, the press release he gave me said
此外 他给我提供的新闻稿说
Chen Duxiu Hu Shi, three professors from Qian Xuantong
陈独秀 胡适 钱玄同三位教授
Has been expelled from Peking University.
已经被北京大学开除
Now I want to ask
现在 我想问
Principal Cai Yuanpei, is this a rumor?
蔡元培校长 这是造谣吗
Mr Edward, let me tell you something.
爱德华先生 我告诉你
陈独秀教授
陈独秀教授
Professor Hu Shi
胡适教授
Professor Qian Xuantong
钱玄同教授
Sitting next to me right now.
此时就坐在我身边
They represent Peking University.
他们是代表北京大学
Come here to be questioned.
到这儿来接受质询
So I tell you responsibly.
所以我负责任地告诉你
Those things in your newspaper now
你现在 报纸上那些东西
It's all lies
全是假话
And it's a rumor
而且是谣言
I also received this Zhang Gongzi.
我也收到了这位张公子
Red envelopes and manuscripts from here.
送来的红包和稿件
Although I don't agree.
虽然我并不赞成
New Youth and New Tide
《新青年》和《新潮》
Put forward some ideas
提出的一些主张
But as a journalist
但是作为记者
I firmly oppose the practice of spending money on news.
我坚决反对花钱买新闻的做法
I think
我认为
This is a challenge to journalists' moral bottom line.
这是对记者道德底线的一种挑战
I prove
我证明
The report about Peking University published by our newspaper
我们报社刊登的关于北大的报道
Zhang Fengzai paid for them all.
都是张丰载花钱买到的
Look
你们看
This is what he offered us.
这就是他给我们提供的
Manuscript on today's congressional inquiry
关于今天国会质询的稿件
And the contributions provided by these two journalists.
和这两位记者提供的稿件
Is the same.
是一样的
Zhang Changli you are shameless.
张长礼 你无耻
They are lying.
他们在撒谎
Don't trust them.
不要相信他们
beat you to death
打死你
cook up a story
造谣
tell a lie
撒谎
beat you to death
打死你
shameless
无耻
tell a lie
撒谎
Shameless
无耻 无耻
We can't make this noise any longer.
不能再这么闹下去了
Let's finish the meeting.
快散会吧
Ba San ba
散吧 散吧
Since Yi Long is absent for some reason
既然易夔龙因故缺席
Then today's question will be dismissed.
那么今天的质询会散会
Can't dismiss
不能散会
Yi long zai zhe
易夔龙在此
My dad is here.
我爸来了
Coming. mr. yi is coming.
来了 易先生来了
Long Xiong
夔龙兄
Dear Mr. Speaker
尊敬的议长先生
Dear Members of Parliament
尊敬的各位议员
I'm late.
非常抱歉 我来晚了
Long Xiong
夔龙兄
Just waiting for you to explain the proposal.
就等着你做提案说明呢
Now please, Mr. Yi Long
现在请易夔龙议员
Explain the proposal to impeach Cai Yuanpei
做弹劾蔡元培的提案说明
Members of Parliament
各位议员
I'm not here to explain the proposal today.
今天我不是来做提案说明的
I'm here to plead guilty to Mr Cai Yuanpei.
我是来向蔡元培先生请罪的
Because I was confused for a moment
由于我一时糊涂
Ghost lost his heart
鬼迷了心窍
Be deceived by Zhang Changli.
受到了张长礼的欺骗
It was written in Zhang Changli.
在张长礼写好了的
On the proposal of impeaching President Cai to expel Chen Duxiu
弹劾蔡校长驱逐陈独秀的提案上
I signed it.
我签了名
As cannon fodder for him.
给他当了炮灰
Here today.
今天在这里
I formally submit to the Minister of Education of Fu Zengxiang
我正式地向傅增湘教育总长
To Mr. Chen Duxiu, President Cai
向蔡校长 陈独秀先生道歉
Another day, I'll pay you a courtesy call.
改日还当分别登门负荆请罪
Yi kuilong
易夔龙
You've gone back on your word.
你出尔反尔 而口喷人
Extremely shameless
无耻至极
shameless
无耻
You are shameless.
你才无耻呢
Ah, it's just because I miss women badly.
是啊 只因我思女心切
I was taken in by you.
才上了你的当
Did a bad thing to frame Zhongliang.
做了一件诬陷忠良的坏事
I'm really shameless
我确实无耻啊
Yi kuilong
易夔龙
Which one did you sing?
你到底唱的哪一出啊
Explain it to all of us.
你跟我们大家解释清楚
explain away
对
make it clear
说清楚
Ladies and gentlemen
诸位 诸位诸位
Please allow me to talk about this matter.
请允许我把这件事情说一说
Xiaoqunxian
小女群先
Dissatisfied with the arranged marriage I gave her
因不满我给她的包办婚姻
run away from home
离家出走
I'm in a hurry.
我是急得六神无主啊
At this time
这个时候
Zhang Changli and his nephew ran to tell me that
张长礼和他的侄儿跑来告诉我说
The little girl has suffered.
小女受到了
Cai Yuanpei's "bewitched by Chen Duxiu"
蔡元培 陈独秀的蛊惑
Participated in the work-study mutual aid society initiated by Cai Yuanpei.
参加了由蔡元培发起的工读互助社
Also said
还说
This mutual aid society is controlled by foreign religions.
这个互助社是受到洋教的控制
Eliminate family and communist hetaerism.
实行消灭家庭 共产共妻
The doctrine of losing human relations
丧失人伦的教义
They also gave me a lot.
他们还给了我许多
Newspapers and leaflets attacking President Cai and Mr. Chen
攻击蔡校长和陈先生的报纸和传单
If we don't bring down Cai Yuanpei and Chen Duxiu
说如果不扳倒蔡元培和陈独秀
My little girl will never return to her family.
我的小女就永远都不能回归家庭
Countless young people will be brought into the abyss of sin.
无数的青年将被带入罪恶的深渊
I'm the only daughter in the group.
我就群先这么一个女儿
Listen to the bewitch of Zhang Changli.
听了张长礼的蛊惑
In a fit of pique, I swore a poison oath.
一气之下我就发了毒誓
Desperate to bring down Cai Yuanpei.
拼死也要扳倒蔡元培
In this way, I am in what he has already written
就这样 我在他已经写好了的
Sign the proposal.
提案上签了名
I did a stupid thing.
我做了一件大蠢事啊
Thanks to Mr. Zhang Shizhao's teaching regret.
幸得章士钊先生教悔
That's the truth.
这才真相大白
I am ashamed of President Cai.
我愧对蔡校长
I am ashamed of Mr. Chen.
我愧对陈先生
I am even more ashamed of my daughter.
我更愧对我的女儿
I'm here today to officially announce
今天在这里我正式地宣布
Withdraw this ridiculous proposal.
撤销这个荒唐的提案
And make a profound review to parliament.
并向议会做出深刻的检讨
Dad said it well.
爸爸说得好
Zhang Changli is shameless
张长礼无耻
Everybody take it easy.
大家别激动
Everybody, listen to me.
大家听我说啊
We invite Mr. Zhang Changli
我们请张长礼议员
Can you explain it to us?
给我们解释一下好不好
Zhang Changli explained
张长礼 解释解释
Explain
解释 解释
Explain what situation clearly.
什么情况解释清楚
everyone
各位
I do have an unshirkable responsibility for this matter.
这件事我的确有不可推卸的责任
This is my little nephew Zhang Fengzai.
这是我的小侄张丰载
Brother Changli
长礼兄
He is a student of Peking University.
他是北大的学生
I mistakenly believed his evasive remarks.
我误信了他的逸言
At the same time, he was misled by Mr. Lin Lao's novels.
同时也受林纾老先生小说的误导
I was kind.
我是好心哪
Good intentions do bad things.
好心做了坏事
I will review it with parliament.
我向议会检讨
Also to Speaker Tian of the Parliament.
也向议会的田议长致
What should be more apologetic is that
更应该致歉的是
The wronged President Cai Yuanpei
受了委屈的蔡元培校长
陈独秀教授
陈独秀教授
To you
向你们致
To professor Li Dazhao
向李大钊教授
Professor Hu Shi
胡适教授
apologize
致歉
I agree with Mr Yi Long.
我同意易龙议员
Proposed decision to withdraw
提出撤销的决定
Unfortunately, my family's family has this perverse son.
我张家家门不幸 出此性逆之子
I'll go back and make a law to punish him.
我回去定当家法惩治他
Di-t
二叔
Brother Chang Li, brother Chang Li
长礼兄 长礼兄
Uncle, uncle, brother Chang Li
二叔 二叔 长礼兄
Hold on, hold on.
快快快 扶着
Take the hospital to the hospital.
送医院 送医院
Severely punish Zhang Changli
严惩张长礼
Since the proposal is withdrawn
既然提案撤销
The meeting is now adjourned.
现在 散会
wait a minute
等一下
You've ruined enough.
你们诋毁够了
Enough noise, too.
也闹腾够了
Should we say something?
应该我们说几句了吧
Journalists and friends, don't get me wrong.
各位记者朋友 别误会
This is the Senate.
这里是国会参议院
Not a free market.
不是自由市场
I'm sure you don't want to come by yourself.
想必你们也不想自来一趟
Nothing, huh?
一无所获是吧
I'm standing here today
今天我站在这儿了
Please feel free to ask any questions.
有什么问题尽管问
陈独秀学长
陈独秀学长
Excuse me, Peking University and New Youth
请问北京大学和 《新青年》
What is the relationship?
到底是什么关系
"New Youth" is really written by Peking University.
《新青年》确实是由北京大学
Some professors practice peer editing.
一些教授实行同人编辑的
But "New Youth"
但是《新青年》
It is an independent magazine.
是一份经营独立的杂志
It has no affiliation with Peking University.
它与北京大学没有隶属关系
"New Youth" All Bai's actions
《新青年》的一切行为
All are in the charge of its editorial department.
均由它的编辑部负责
Has nothing to do with any other unit.
与其他任何单位无涉
Excuse me, Mr. Chen Duxiu
请问陈独秀先生
I've seen a lot recently.
最近我看到许多
Not conducive to New Youth magazine
不利于 《新青年》 杂志的
Articles and reports
文章和报道
I want to know what you think of these criticisms.
我想知道你怎么看待这些非难
And "New Youth" over the past three years
以及 《新青年》 这三年来
What on earth have you done?
究竟做了些什么
Over the past three years
这三年来
This journal is called destructive magazine by some people.
本志被某些人称之为破坏性杂志
We say we destroy Confucianism.
说我们破坏孔教
Destroy etiquette
破坏礼法
Destroy the quintessence of the country
破坏国粹
Destroy chastity
破坏贞节
Breaking the old ethics
破环旧伦理
Destroy old art
破坏旧艺术
Destroy the old religion
破坏旧宗教
Destroy old literature
破坏旧文学
Destroy old politics
破坏旧政治
For these
对于这些
Of course, we people with the same ambition will recognize it directly.
我们本志同人当然直认不
Why should we destroy these things?
我们为什么要破坏这些东西
Only because we support Demokrasi.
只因为我们拥护德莫克拉西
And two gentlemen, Seines.
和赛因斯两位先生
You should support Mr. and Mr. Sai.
你要拥护德先生和赛先生
You have to oppose the old ideas.
你就不得不反对旧的思想
Old literature
旧的文学
What has Ben Zhi done in the past three years?
要说本志这三年到底做了些什么
That's all.
无非就是这些
in my opinion
在我看来
Promoting democracy and science in present China
在当下的中国推行民主和科学
It's a difficult or even dangerous thing.
是很困难甚至是很危险的事情
Will Mr. Chen insist?
陈先生 你会坚持吗
good
好
Westerners support Desai, gentlemen
西洋人因为拥护德赛两位先生
How many things have happened?
闹了多少事
How much blood did you lose?
流了多少血
Mr. Desai and Mr. Desai gradually
德先生和赛先生才渐渐地
Save them from the darkness.
把他们从黑暗中救出
To the bright world
到光明世界
We now believe that
我们现在认定
Only two gentlemen Desai.
只有德赛两位先生
Can cure China politically and morally
可以救治中国在政治上 道德上
All the darkness in academic thought.
学术上 思想上的一切黑暗
Because if you support two gentlemen
若因为拥护两位先生
Persecution by all reactionary governments
一切反动政府的迫害
Social attacks and abuse
社会的攻击和漫骂
We don't refuse
我们都不推辞
good
好
I would like to ask Mr. Li Dazhao a question.
我想请问李大钊先生一个问题
I've read a lot of articles written by you recently.
最近我读了不少您写的文章
You feel very interested in Marxism.
感到您对马克思主义很感兴趣
There are many praises for the October Revolution in Russia.
对俄国十月革命多有赞美之词
I want to ask Mr. Li.
我想请教李先生
Are you a follower of Marxism?
您是马克思主义的信徒吗
As a reader who pursues the truth
作为一个追求真理的读书者
I won't hide my views at all.
我丝毫不会隐瞒自己的观点
Although my knowledge of Marxism
虽然我对马克思主义的认识
Still superficial.
还很肤浅
But I think ...
但是我认为
Marxism
马克思主义
Is the most scientific theory in the world.
是世界上最科学的理论
Russian October Revolution
俄国十月革命
A social system based on Marxism
依据马克思主义创建的社会制度
And so far.
也是迄今为止
The highest system of human social system
人类社会制度的最高制度
I am fascinated by this.
对此 我心驰神往
good
好
Mr. Chen
陈先生
I know you are advocating the new culture movement.
我知道您在倡导新文化运动
I really want to know
我很想知道
You hope the new culture movement
你希望新文化运动
To the development of Chinese society
对中国社会的发展
What kind of impact will it have?
会产生什么样的影响
Probably understood.
大概听懂了
Influence of New Culture Movement on China
新文化运动对中国的影响力
Of course, it is not limited to culture.
当然绝不仅仅局限于文化方面
The new culture movement affected the industry.
新文化运动影响到产业上
Workers should be awakened.
应该令劳动者觉悟
Their own position
他们自己的地位
Make capitalists turn laborers
令资本家把劳动者
Treat them as their kind.
当成他们同类人看待
Don't think of it as a robot.
而不要当成机器 牛马
Slave to look at
奴隶来看待
The new culture movement affected politics.
新文化运动影响到政治上
Is to create new political ideas.
是要创造新的政治思想
Don't be influenced by real politics.
不要被现实的政治羁绊
What is realistic politics?
什么是现实的政治
Such as the current realistic politics.
臂如当下的现实政治
That's a group of boring spectators with no food.
那就是一班没有饭吃的无聊看客
Where are rumors causing trouble?
在那儿造谣生事
And people's life and political ideals.
与人民的生活和政治理想
It doesn't matter.
都毫无关系
But politicians of all factions.
不过是各派的政客
Have soldiers of all factions.
拥有了各派的军人
Struggle for power and profit
在争权夺利
It's like a dog fighting for a bone
如同狗争骨头一般而已
Their competition is dog's sport.
他们的争夺 是狗的运动
The new culture movement is a human movement.
新文化运动是人的运动
We should only take people's sports.
我们只应该拿人的运动
To disperse the dog's movement.
去轰散狗的运动
We should not abandon our people's movement.
而不应该抛弃我们人的运动
To join their dog's movement.
来加入他们狗的运动
Okay, okay, okay.
好 好 好
win
赢了
We won
我们赢了
We won, we won, we won
我们赢了 我们赢了 我们赢了
Brother Zhongfu's speech in the parliament
仲甫兄在议会上那番讲话呀
He put "New Youth"
他把《新青年》
To put aside the relationship with Peking University.
和北大的关系给撇开
In doing so, he considered the problem very comprehensively.
他这样做考虑问题还是很全面的
Actually, I know what he meant.
其实我特别明白他的意思
Now let's "New Youth"
现在咱们 《新青年》
In the eyes of the government
在政府的眼里头
Is a scourge.
就是洪水猛兽
We can't tie ourselves up.
我们自己不能束缚自己呀
Put aside the relationship.
撇开关系之后
We can let go of our fighting power.
我们就可以放手战斗了
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
In Lin's "Gong Yan Bao"
林纾在《公言报》上
Published his open letter.
发布了他的公开信
Apologize to you
给您道歉了
What did he say?
他说些什么呢
This is how he explained it.
他是这么解释的
In recent years
最近几年
Because I've heard a lot.
因为耳闻目了许多
Weigh the words and deeds of the old culture
秤击旧文化的言行
It's a little too much for him.
让他有点忍无可忍了
So in a rage
所以一怒之下
I made a lot of false statements.
就发布了很多不实的言论
Give it to Peking University.
给您和北大
Has brought a lot of bad effects.
带来了很多不好的影响
He hoped you would forgive me.
他十分抱歉 希望您能原谅
At the same time he insisted
同时他还坚持
He insisted on opposing the new culture.
坚持他反对新文化的观点
He also said
他还表示
Fight for the rest of my life and stick to my ambition.
拼其残年 坚守其志
Will silence the tongue.
必使反舌无声
The dog didn't bark before it died.
瘈狗不吠而后已
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
It seems that this old Mr. Lin
看来这个林老先生
Is an opponent worthy of our admiration.
是值得我们敬佩的对手
Caigong
蔡公
Cai
蔡
Shenshu
申叔
Caigong
蔡公
Uncle Shen, what's wrong with your body?
申叔 你身体怎么了
Slight ailment
微恙 微恙
Cai Gong wrote a letter.
蔡公 我写了封信
I wanted to give it to you.
本想交给你
Everyone is here today.
今天各位都在
Let's read it to everyone.
不妨念给大家听听
good
好
"Gong Yan Bao" is the leading writer.
《公言报》主笔大鉴
Read your 18th newspaper.
读十八日贵报
A change of ideological trend in Beijing academic circles
北京学界思潮变迁一则
More inconsistent with the facts.
多与事实不符
Although the county people are the university chairs.
郡人虽主大学讲席
However, Luo Yu closed the door and thanked the guests.
然抱疾罗余 闭关谢客
Teachers in the school seldom contact with each other.
于校中教员素鲜接洽
An-you-have-a-combination thing
安有结合之事
Another monthly magazine, National Heritage
又《国故》月刊
Initiated by liberal arts students
由文科学员发起
Although preserving the quintessence of Chinese culture is Zongchang
虽以保存国粹为宗旨
亦非与《新潮》诸杂志
亦非与《新潮》诸杂志
Argue with each other
互相争辩也
That is to say, praying for correction is the most important thing.
祈即查找更正 是为至荷
Liu Shipei qi
刘师培启
Cai and I have one more thing to declare.
蔡公 我还有一事要声明
Go ahead.
你请说
If Chen Zhongfu insists on his way,
如果陈仲甫还要坚持他那一套
Liu Shipei will fight him to the end.
我刘师培愿与他战斗到底
Uncle Shen, I believe that with brother Zhongfu's character
申叔兄 我相信以仲甫兄的性格
I will fight with you to the end.
一定也会与您斗争到底的
say goodbye to
告辞
All right, all right, we've said what we have to say.
好了好了 我们该说的也说了
I'm thinking.
我在想啊
Should we treat Zhang Fengzai as the mole?
我们是不是该对张丰载这个内鬼
Have made a statement.
有个表态了
Mr. Cai
蔡先生
People like Zhang Fengzai
张丰载这样的人
Peking University will never tolerate it.
我们北大绝不姑息养好
Please, please
请 请 请
Councillor Zhang's coming here late at night is really glorious.
张议员深夜到此真是蓬荜生辉
Please sit down, please sit down.
快请坐 快请坐
Please, please
请 请 请
I wonder if Zhang has good tea for me.
不知张 对 我有好茶
No, no, no, no need.
不不不 不必
No, no, please sit down.
不必了不必了 请坐
Brother Jing Tan
镜潭兄呀
Late night visits don't smell bad.
深夜造访 不揣冒昧
This is my nephew Zhang Fengzai.
这是小侄张丰载
I have something to report to you.
有一事向你禀报
Uncle Wu is good.
吴叔叔好
Sit.
坐 坐
I've long heard about your great name
久闻大名
I heard that my good nephew was killed by an adulterer.
我听说贤侄被奸人所害
Forced to leave Peking University.
被迫离开了北大
There are many people who cry out for you.
有不少人为你叫屈喊冤哪
Actually, that's not true, Uncle Wu.
其实不是这样的吴叔叔
Expelled
开除的
my worthy nephew
贤侄
Gold shines everywhere.
是金子到什么地方都会发光
The official announcement of the peace conference has arrived.
和会正式的通知到了
Let me read it to you.
我来给大家念念
Chinese delegation
中国代表团
Two proposals made by your delegation
贵代表团所提两项提案
That is, request abolition.
即请求废除
May 25th, 195
一九一五年五月二十五日
A treaty signed by the Chinese and Japanese governments
中日两国政府所签订之条约
Exchange articles and posts
及换文说帖
Hope condition post
希望条件说帖
Are not within the authority of the Peace Conference.
均不在和会权限之内
At best, the summit will recognize
和会最高会议充其量承认
The importance of these two proposals
此两项提案的重要性
But it can't be settled in peace.
但不能在和会解决
Request the administration department of the Federation of Nations
拟请万国联合会行政部
When you can exercise your authority
能行使职权时
Please pay attention to China's position.
请其注意中国的立场
So both proposals were rejected.
这么说这两项提案都被驳回了
Then we ...
那我们
What are you still doing here?
还在这儿千什么呢
Monso also said
克里孟梭还说
Japan represents Mu Ye.
日本代表牧野
At the meeting of ten people this morning.
在今天上午十人会议上提出
Japan should fully accept
日本应该全面接收
Germany's leased land in Shandong
德国在山东的租借地
And hopes and will support Japan's position.
并希望和会支持日本的立场
Proposal for Japan
针对日本的提议
Mr Williams, consultant of American delegation, suggested
美国代表团顾问威廉斯先生建议
The Chinese representative should be invited.
应该请中国代表
Attend the debate meeting at three o'clock this afternoon.
参加今天下午三点的争辩会
And state China's position.
并单述中国的立场
stand a chance
有希望
So this American
这么说这个美国人
It's interesting enough
还够点意思
The Secretary-General of CPC has given the Chinese delegation
和会秘书长已经给中国代表团
Send an official invitation to the meeting.
发来列会会议的正式邀请函
Two people will be listed.
列会人员两人
Only one of them has the right to speak.
其中只有一人有发言权
What the government means is
政府的意思是
Please minister Gu attend with me.
请顾公使和我一同出席
Minister Gu spoke.
由顾公使发言
I agree
我同意
Do you have any comments?
你有什么意见吗
Then please, you two.
那就拜托二位了
Since everyone is okay with it
既然大家都没意见
Then let's just let the two of us be reluctant.
那只有让我们两个人勉为其难吧
Nineteen nine
一九一九年
The victorious country held a peace conference in Paris.
战胜国在巴黎召开和会
This time by Britain, France, America and Italy
在这次由英法美意
At the meeting controlled by the Big Four
四巨头掌控的和会上
The world order has been redefined.
世界秩序被重新划定
Originally, before the war, Germany
而原本德国在战前
Obtain the rights and interests of Jiaozhou Bay, Shandong Province, China
取得中国山东胶州湾的权益
It has also become the focus of disputes between China and Japan.
也成为中日争执的焦点
The Japanese delegation proposed
日本代表团提出
Japan should inherit German rights and interests.
日本应当继承德国权益
On behalf of Gu Weijun, China argued.
中国代表顾维钧据理力争
Refute Japan's demands one by one.
逐条批驳日本的要求
He pointed out
他指出
No matter from the history of Shandong
无论从山东的历史
Geographical and cultural aspects
地理 文化方面
Or from China to Germany?
还是从中国对于德国
In terms of being a victorious country.
处于战胜国的地位而言
Jiaozhou leased land
胶州租借地
Jiaozhou railway
胶州铁路
And all other rights.
及其他一切权利
It should be returned to China directly.
应直接交还中国
But the Beiyang government
但北洋政府
Pro-Japanese Cao Rulin, etc
亲日派曹汝霖等
Unde that pressure of Japan
在日本压力下
Said the move was purely unauthorized.
却说此举纯属擅自行动
Yi Jun's speech
颐维钧的发言
Caused great dissatisfaction in this government.
引起了日本政府极大不满
I ordered Xiao Xiji, Minister in China.
遂命驻华公使小幡酉吉
Put pressure on Beiyang government
向北洋政府施压
chairman of the committee
委员长
great-uncle
伯公
The younger generation really has one.
晚辈实在是有一件
I don't know what to do with it.
不知如何处置之事
Come to ask for advice.
特来登门讨教
I know that Japanese minister Koji has come here.
我知道 日本公使小幡闯关来了
You're scared.
把你给吓着了
What did Xiao Yan say?
小幡都说什么了
Xiao Yan said
小幡说
Gu Weijun is going to give a French press conference
顾维钧要在法国记者招待会上
Announce the secret agreement between China and Japan
公布中日密约
He instructed Takamoto.
他奉日本训令
Ask the Chinese government to call the delegation.
要求中国政府致电代表团
watch your step and mind what you are saying
谨言慎行
They were impressed by the performance of the Chinese delegation in Paris.
他们对中国代表团在巴黎的表现
Express special dissatisfaction
表示特别不满
Make a solemn protest
提出严正的抗议
And threatened to
还威胁说
Take 1918.
要把一九一八年
Zongxiang personally signed it.
章宗祥亲手签订的
The agreement on the Shandong issue between China and Japan was made public.
中日山东问题的协议公布于众
In fact, this matter is very powerful.
其实这件事情很好力
Some people in the government are afraid of Japan
政府里有人怕日本
Chinese people are not afraid of Japan.
中国人民并不怕日本
Sell newspapers
卖报卖报
Japan's Minister Koji
日本公使小幡
Put pressure on Chen Zhuan
向陈箓施压
Look at the local business associations.
看各地学联商团
Letter to the Chinese delegation of Paris Peace Conference
致信巴黎和会中国代表团
Ask the Chinese representative to resist the pressure.
要求中国代表顶住压力
Never betray a country
绝不卖国
Sell newspapers sell newspapers.
卖报 卖报卖报
Japanese minister Xiao
日本公使小
Put pressure on Chen Zhuan
向陈箓施压
Look at the local business associations.
看各地学联 商团
Letter to the Chinese delegation of Paris Peace Conference
致信巴黎和会中国代表团
Fellow students
各位同学
Let me read it out below.
下面我宣读
All students in Peking University
北京大学全体学生
Open letter to the Chinese delegation of Paris Peace Conference
致巴黎和会中国代表团公开信
Delegates
诸位代表
All the students in Peking University in recent days
连日来北京大学全体学生
I heard that you were brilliant at the peace conference.
听闻列位在和会上精彩论
I complain about my rights and interests in Shandong.
申诉我对山东之权益
Be deeply excited
深感振奋
Your performance
诸位之表现
It is an example for young Chinese students.
实乃我中国青年学生之表率
Recently, there was a Japanese minister
近日 发生有日本公使
Forcing my foreign ministry to scare me.
强闯我外交部恫吓一事
We hope that all delegates will be the best at pressing the party.
但方望各位代表顶住压力
Never allow Japan to occupy Shandong.
绝不可答应日本霸占山东之要求
Shandong and Qingdao issues
山东及青岛问题
It concerns the survival of our country.
关系我国存亡
Strive for sovereignty.
主权所在 务恳力争
All students in Peking University are the same
北京大学全体学生同叩
classmates
同学们
For special attention
为了特续关注
Development of the Paris Peace Conference
巴黎和会事态的发展
In order to better organize everyone
为了更好地组织各位
Let everyone know the truth of the situation for the first time.
让大家第一时间了解事态的真相
At this gathering, we
我们在此次集会中
More than ten student union officers were launched.
公推出十余名学生会干事
So as to unite with universities in Beijing.
以便联合北京各大高校
Take concerted action
采取一致行动
Welcome
大家欢迎
Today, we are elected as directors.
今日 大家公推我们几位为干事
We are both excited and scared.
我们既觉得兴奋也觉得煌恐
Feel the great responsibility on one's shoulders
[赵世炎 字 琴生 北京高等师范附中学生]
But please believe us.
但请各位相信我们
We will fight with all our strength to fulfill our mission.
我们必定不辱使命 全力而战
Pledge to resist Japan and defend Shandong
誓死抵制日本 保卫山东
I give the floor to Mr. Li Dazhao.
下面 请李大钊先生发言
classmates
同学们
A peace conference in Paris
在巴黎召开的和会
It's our first time in China.
是我们中国第一次
An international conference attended as a victorious country.
以战胜国的身份参加的国际大会
So since it's an international conference
那么既然是国际大会
Countries safeguard their national interests at the meeting.
各国在会上维护自己国家的利益
Put forward one's correct opinion.
提出自己正确的主张
It is the important principle that countries should be independent.
乃是各国独立应存之大义
There is no reason for his country to interfere.
他国 绝无干涉的道理
But just because
可是就是因为
Our Gu Weijun Gu envoy.
我们的顾维钧顾专使
Represents all of us Chinese.
代表了我们全体中国人
Appeal at the Paris Peace Conference
在巴黎和会上申诉
To recover our rights and interests in Shandong.
要收回我们直已山东的权益
The Japanese actually asked to replace him.
日本人竟然要求要撤换他
Boys and girls, say
同学们 你们说
Our 400 million Chinese compatriots
我们四万万中国同胞
Can you promise?
能够答应吗
cannot
不能
At this conference advocating world fairness
在这个提倡世界公平的大会上
We have put forward the correct proposition of our country.
我们提出了自己国家正确的主张
The Japanese rushed into our Foreign Ministry.
日本人竟然冲进了我们的外交部
The Present Continuous Tense
进行桐吓
Carry out tongxia
威逼我们屈服
Boys and girls, say
同学们 你们说
Can our 400 million Chinese compatriots be intimidated?
我们四万万中国同胞能被吓倒吗
cannot
不能
Japan claims to have a million troops.
日本号称有陆军百万
Be ready to fight.
随时准备应战
To intimidate us into giving up the rights and interests of Shandong.
以威逼我们放弃山东的权益
classmates
同学们
You said we could give in because of it.
你们说 我们能够因此而屈服
Are you afraid of it?
因此而惧怕吗
No, no, no
不能 不能 不能
This Wang Daxie sends three telegrams a day.
这个汪大燮一天三封电报
Let me get back to Paris.
非让我赶回巴黎
What's the matter? This is
怎么了这是
What's the matter
出什么事了
Chief Lu is not what's the big deal?
陆总长 不是出了什么大事
And there are important things you need to decide.
而且有大事需要您来定夺
Request to abolish May 25th, 1915
请求废除一九一五年五月二十五日
A treaty signed by the Chinese and Japanese governments
中日两国政府所签订的条约
Exchange articles and posts
及换文说帖
Hope condition post
希望条件说帖
Do you want to send it again after being rejected?
被驳回以后要不要再送
There is no opinion in the regiment
团内意见不一
I can't coordinate, so I have to ask you to come out.
我无力协调 只能请您出山
I read the post on Shandong issue.
我看 山东问题的说帖
Signed with China and Japan
和中日签订
Various secret agreements on the Shandong issue
有关山东问题的各项密约
Let's put it on hold.
还是先放一放
Don't send it to the peace conference for the time being.
暂时不要送交和会
It is advisable to wait until the Japanese side agrees to deliver it.
等日方同意 再送交为宜
Minister Hu really is
胡公使果真是
Frightened by the Japanese minister.
被日本公使给吓着了
I'm also thinking of the country.
我也是为国家着想
If the Japanese do send troops
要是日本人真的出兵
Then the situation will be difficult to clean up.
那么局面就不好收拾
Besides, the government is still hesitating.
况且政府还在犹豫不决
Let's take a long-term view.
我们还是 从长计议吧
A telegram has just arrived.
刚刚送来电报
I wonder if you have seen it.
不知诸位看了没有
Minister from Japan
自日本小幡公使
Since tung's scare was published in the newspaper.
桐吓之事登报以来
The jade people are in high spirits.
国内民众群情高涨
Send telegrams to the delegation.
纷纷给代表团打电报
I have received dozens of letters in the past few days.
就这几日 已经收到了几十封
An article is painful and interesting, and words are willing to cut.
篇篇痛陈利害 言辞愿切
We ask to resist the pressure.
要求我们顶住压力
This is just received.
这是刚收到的
Telegrams from students in Peking University.
北京大学学生发来的电报
We must never agree to the request.
要求我们绝不能答应
Japan's demand for occupying Shandong
日本霸占山东之要求
Even young students know.
连青年学生都知道
Shandong and Qingdao asked
山东及青岛问题
It concerns the survival of our country.
关系到我国的存亡
Why did Minister Hu hesitate?
胡公使却为何犹豫呢
My heart for my country is bright.
我为国家之心 天日可表
Don't you all understand?
难道大家还不明白吗
Xin Wu Shao chuan
馨吾 少川
Everybody listen to me.
大家都听我说
This matter must not please the Japanese.
此事断不可讨好日本人
Now the participating countries
现在与会各国
Have expressed sympathy for us.
纷纷对我们表示同情
If we can't insist at this time
如果此时我们不能坚持
Soften halfway
半途软化
Even if someone else is willing to help me.
即便是有他人愿意助我
It will also make our country lose its international reputation.
也会让我国损失在国际上的声誉
What will we have then?
到时我们还有什么面目
Ask for help from other countries?
去要求别国的援助呢
Two evils
两害相权
My opinion is
我的意见是
Send a post again
再送说帖
be
是
I
我
I'll find Wilson.
我去找威尔逊
After Xiaoyou Jitong scared the Beiyang government
继小幡酉吉桐吓北洋政府后
The Japanese delegation once again proposed at the peace conference
日本代表团再次在和会上提出
To Germany's rights and interests in Shandong, China
要将德国在中国山东的权益
Handed over to Japan
移交给日本
And Wilson in order to limit Ben
而威尔逊为了限制日本
Expansion momentum in East Asia
在东亚的扩张势头
At the beginning of the peace conference
在和会初期
Rejected Japan's request
一度拒绝了日本的要求
Mohism in Pre-Qin Dynasty
墨家学说在先秦
Write Confucianism and call it outstanding.
写儒家并称显学
Mohism takes universal love as its core.
墨家学说以兼爱为核心
Take saving Shang Xian as the fulcrum
以节用 尚贤为支点
There are ten propositions, please see.
共有十大主张 请看
Love and not attack
兼爱 非攻
Shang Xian Shang Tong
尚贤 尚同
Respect the ghost of heaven.
尊天 事鬼
Be happy and unhappy.
非乐 非命
Festive burial
节用 节葬
Universal love is the core of family theory.
兼爱 是墨家学说的核心
The so-called universal love
所谓兼爱
It contains the meaning of equality and fraternity
它包含了平等和博爱的意思
Mohism asked the monarch, minister and son.
墨家要求君臣 父子
Between brothers
兄弟之间
We should love each other on the basis of equality.
都要在平等的基础上相互友爱
If a lover loves his body.
爱人若爱其身
And think that in society
并且认为在社会上
If there is a strong, weak, rich and poor regret
如果出现了强执弱 富悔贫
The phenomenon of high and low
贵傲贱的现象
Because people don't love each other.
是因为天下人不相爱所致
Sir, one thing is unknown to the students.
先生 学生有一事不明
Oriental people and westerners are dominating me, and Shandong won't pay me back.
东洋人西洋人都霸着我山东不还
This is a typical strong-willed behavior.
这是典型的强执弱行为
Is this what Mr. Wang said?
难道这也是先生所讲的
Don't people love what they do?
天下人不爱所为吗
classmates
同学们
Guo Xingang classmate
郭心刚同学
I raised questions in class today.
今天在课堂上提出了问题
This is a good thing.
这是好事
Prove that Guo Xingang has started to think.
证明郭心刚同学已经开始思考了
But classmate Guo
但是郭同学
Today's question is beside the point.
你今天的问题跑题了
Today we are talking about ancient Chinese philosophy.
今天我们讲的是中国古代哲学
It's an academic issue.
是学界讨论的问题
What you said just now is a political issue.
你刚才说的是政治问题